Preliminary Guide to the James T. Cleland papers, 1928-1975
Duke University. University Archives
James T. Cleland papers 1928-1975
Cleland, James T. (James Tough), 1903-
50 linear feet Extent: 50,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Contains personal and professional papers relating to the life and work of James Tough Cleland, preacher, Dean of the Duke University Chapel (1955-1973), and Professor of Preaching in the Divinity School (1945-1968). Materials include addresses, sermons, lecture notes, speeches, clippings, printed materials, correspondence, a tape recording, committee records, course materials, photographs, subject files, a scrapbook, diaries, and gift albums. Albums include sketches, engravings, frontispieces, and colored illustrations from printed materials. Major subjects include armed forces chaplains, hospital chaplains, death and dying, euthanasia, spirituality, Christianity, the study and teaching of the book of Paul, the study and teaching of the Bible, study and teaching of preaching, Duke University Chapel, Duke University, and the Divinity School. Materials range in date from 1825 to 1982 (bulk 1928-1975). Contains restricted materials. English.
uacleland
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The James T. Cleland papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1959-1999 (59-25, 68-338, 72-4, 72-5, 72-26, 74-23, 74-103, 75-9, 79-69, 79-134, 84-87, 85-25, 87-9, 94-47, A99-50).
Biographical Note
James Tough Cleland was born on July 8, 1903 in Glasgow, Scotland to the Rev. James Cleland and Margaret Curdie Cleland. He married Alice Mean on September 7, 1932. Cleland earned degrees from Glasgow University (M.A., 1924 and Ecclesiastical History, with distinction, B.D., 1927) and Union Theological Seminary, New York (S.T.M., summa cum laude, 1928, and Th.D., 1954).
After 14 years in the religion department at Amherst College, he arrived at Duke in 1945. At Duke, Cleland was Professor of Preaching in the Divinity School from 1945 to 1968. After his 1968 retirement, he became Professor Emeritus. He was also Dean of the Duke University Chapel from 1955 until 1973, and was the only person to hold both positions. His honors at Duke University included the James B. Duke professorship, Omicron Delta Kappa, Phi Beta Kappa, Order of Red Friars, and Alpha Omega Alpha.
Cleland held many lectureships at international pulpits. He was a guest of the United States Army, Navy, and Air Force Chiefs of Chaplains as preacher at each of the service academies. He also conducted worship services at the Air Force's most northern location (Thule, Greenland) and professional seminars for Air Force Chaplains in Alaska, Japan, and Philippines. Additionally, Dr. Cleland delivered the opening prayer for the U.S. Senate (January 19, 1960) and gave sermons at debutante balls, military chapels, college and university chapels, and at preparatory schools. Throughout his career, he was in constant demand by students and alumni as well as churches, prep schools, and colleges on the east coast. One year he preached 13 baccalaureate sermons; he preached one sermon 86 times.
Some of Dr. Cleland's writings include a biography of James H. Tufts, The True and Lively Word, Wherefore Art Thou Come?, Preaching to be Understood, and He Died as He Lived. He wrote three exposition sections in Volumes II and VI of The Interpreter's Bible. He has had sermons published in five volumes of Best Sermons. He has also contributed 86 articles to "Preaching Clinic" in The Chaplain, a periodical for all United States Military Chaplains. His areas of research included the Epistles of Paul, preaching to groups, chaplain education, and interdenominational church groups. He also consulted with chaplains and doctors about care for terminally ill patients and death with dignity.
The Cleland family traveled internationally, keeping detailed journals of daily events. During 1938-1939, they traveled to Europe and the Middle East where they recorded interactions with Nazi party members and German Jews. The Cleland's travels to the Philippines and Japan gives insight into the U.S. military during the Vietnam War. The Clelands also made many trips from the United States to Scotland and England. James Cleland was frequently called to preach around the United States and the Clelands made vacations of these trips.
In spring 1973, after 28 years of dedicated and distinguished service to Duke University, Dr. Cleland retired. He continued to serve as dean of the chapel for several more years.
Brown House on Duke University's East Campus was renamed "Cleland House" after Dr. James T. Cleland. Dr. Cleland and his wife were advisors to the students of Brown House.
When Cleland died in 1974, the James T. Cleland Chapel Endowment Fund was established in his honor. The fund provides for distinguished visiting preachers and musicians, development of the choral program, and general enrichment of Chapel worship. Cleland was further honored by House Joint Resolution 248, "A Joint Resolution Honoring the Life and Memory of James T. Cleland," on February 27, 1979. The ashes of James T. Cleland, and his wife, Alice M. Cleland, are interred at the Duke University Chapel.
Collection Overview
Contains personal and professional papers relating to the life and work of James T. Cleland, preacher, Dean of the Duke University Chapel (1955-1973), and Professor of Preaching in the Divinity School (1945-1968). Types of materials include addresses, sermons, lecture notes, speeches, clippings, printed materials, correspondence, a tape recording, committee records, course materials, photographs, subject files, a scrapbook, diaries, and gift albums. Gift albums include sketches, engravings, frontispieces, and colored illustrations from printed materials. Materials range in date from 1825 to 1982 (bulk 1928-1975). Box 19 contains restricted materials.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Baccalaureate addresses.; Bible. N.T. Epistles of Paul -- Study and teaching; Bible. N.T. Epistles of Paul -- Theology; Bible. N.T.--Study and teaching; Bible. O.T.--Study and teaching.; Chaplains, Hospital -- North Carolina; Chaplains, Military -- Training of -- United States; Chaplains, Military -- United States; Cleland, James T. (James Tough), 1903-; Death.; Diaries; Duke Chapel (Durham, N.C.); Duke University -- Religious activities; Duke University; Duke University. Chapel; Duke University. Divinity School -- Faculty.; Duke University. Divinity School -- History; Duke University. Medical Center.; Euthanasia -- Moral and ethical aspects -- United States.; Patient advocacy -- North Carolina; Preaching -- Study and teaching; Preaching; Scrapbooks; Sermons; Spirituality; Terminal care; Terminally ill -- Care and treatment
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Subject files A-M (Box 1)
    Includes Alpha Omega Alpha, Davison Club, Death and Dying course, personal and professional correspondence, Music Building speech
  - Subject files N-W (Box 2)
    Includes Cleland Endowment Fund, Chapel Renovation Committee (ca. 1970-1977) Phi Beta Kappa, Phi Kappa Psi, correspondence, "Scotties and Cleland House" (personal writings).
  - Warrack lectures
  - Preaching to be Understood
  - Preaching class notes (PR 29-30, PR 181, PR 185) (Box 3)
  - Assorted subject files
  - Book reviews
  - Preaching class notes (PR 183, PR 185 continued) (Box 4)
  - Subject files, biblical and religious
  - Book reviews
  - Subject files Snow Fund files (Box 5)
  - Snow fund testimonials (Box 6)
  - Subject files including Order of Worship (Duke and non-Duke) (Box 7)
    Includes church worship classes, Human Relations Committee, 1957-1960, Lecture and Publication Events Committee of the Divinity School, personal counseling (L-Z), preaching awards, and the Mary A. Poston Memorial Fund.
  - Chapel budgets, 1958-1968 (Box 8)
  - Chapel organ
  - Materials for The Chaplain
  - Religion 1.15-1.16 lecture notes
  - General history subject files, pre-mechanic and pre-Pauline eras
  - General history subject files, Pauline, post-Pauline (Box 9)
  - Opinion/issue files A-Bi
  - Opinion/issue files Bo-E (Box 10)
  - Opinion/issue files F-M (Box 11)
  - Opinion/issue files N-S (Box 12)
  - Opinion/issue files T-Z (Box 13)
  - Notes for worship classes and public worship, materials from Austin, Texas lectures
  - General subject files, ca. 1970-1972 (Box 14)
    Includes Toastmasters, debutante ball addresses, and religious education
  - General subject files, ca. 1955-1965 (Box 15)
    Includes philosophy, sermons for children, Christian ethics, New Testament, and the Old Testament.
  - Class notes, 1923-1931 (Box 16)
  - General notes on criticism, study, and teaching of Paul
  - Lecture notes, Duke University, ca. 1971-1974 (Box 17)
  - April 21, 1974 service notes
  - Bound volumes of sermons
  - Miscellaneous sermon notes
  - Amherst College Chapel notes
  - Clippings and background material for articles, ca. 1960-1978 (Box 18)
  - Choate chapel talks (Box 19)
  - The True and Lively Word
  - Geriatrics newsletters
  - Wherefore Art Thou Come?
  - Lectures, ca. 1953
  - Personal correspondence, ca. 1924-1938
    RESTRICTED
  - Nick Carter Travel Club, 7" reel tape, 1964
  - General research materials on attitudes toward death
  - Sermon notes (Box 20)
  - Articles on preaching
  - Raw material for sermons on Old Testament and New Testament
  - General subject files on lent, ascension, Ash Wednesday, and Good Friday
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and paper, 1967 (Box 21)
  - Thule, Greenland assignment, 1962
  - Dean of Chapel materials, ca. 1960-1979
  - Wellington Church, Glasgow, Scotland, 1949
  - Letters of appreciation to Cleland, 1960-1976
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, ca. 1960-1979
  - Minutes of Duke University Chapel, 1954-1963, 1967-1978 (Box 22)
  - Duke Alumni and Medical Alumni materials
  - General subject files on spirituality, death, and dying
  - Amherst lectures, 1931-1945, sermon index (Box 23)
  - Sermons (Box 24)
    - Sermons 1-100
    - Sermons 101-189 (Box 25)
    - Sermons 190-275 (Box 26)
    - Sermons 276-350 (Box 27)
    - Sermons 351-413 (Box 28)
  - Diary/gift album of Julia Ann Adriance (Box 29)
  - Diary/gift album of "Thomas"
  - Diary/gift album of Julia Ann Price, 1825
  - Speeches to military chaplains
  - Christmas Eve sermons, 1970-1972
  - Speeches to military chaplains Christmas Eve sermons, 1970-1972
  - Diaries and Correspondence (Box 30)
    - Diaries
      - Great Britain, Germany, Switzerland, Italy, Egypt, Syria, Jerusalem and Palestine.
      - Observations of Nazi Germany, and ordinary Germans and their attitudes toward Jews (6 volumes), 1938-1939
      - Operation Wellington, Trip to Great Britain on the Queen Mary, 1949
      - The California Hegira of the Clelands, Diary of trip while he was Visiting Professor of
      - Preaching, Pacific School of Religion, Berkeley, California, 1951
      - New England and Scotland, 1952
      - Ireland, Scotland, and England, 1956
      - Scotland and England, 1960
      - Chicago, Stratford, Toronto, Gaspe, Cape Breton, and Maine, 1961
      - England, Scotland, Germany, and France. Warrack Lectures in Preaching, Theological
      - Colleges of the Four Scottish Divinity Halls, 1964
      - Conducted Professional Seminar for US Air Force Chaplains in Alaska, Japan, and the Philippines, 1967
    - Correspondence
      - Letters to Alice M. Cleland from Alaska, Japan and the Philippines while away on Professional Seminar for US Air Force Chaplains, 1967
  - Travel diaries, Correspondence, and Personal Material of Alice Mead Cleland (Box 31)
    - Travel diaries
      - "My First Trip Abroad", Europe, June-August, 1929
      - Germany, Switzerland, Italy, Egypt, Syria, Palestine and Jerusalem, 1938-1939
      - Miscellaneous memorabilia and cards from trip June-September, 1949
      - Florida, 1954
      - Ireland, Scotland, and England, 1956
      - Washington, Connecticut, 1958, Vermont, 1959, Chatauqua, Toronto, and Detroit, 1958, 1959, 1969
      - Scotland, England, Germany, and Austria, 1960
      - Great Britain during Warrack lectureship, 1964
      - Great Lakes trips, 1966, 1969
      - Missouri, Indiana and Kentucky, 1974
      - Philadelphia and Bryn Mawr, 1974
      - Edina, Minnesota, 1974
      - Lake Junaluska and Roaring Gap, North Carolina, 1974
      - Davidson College, then to Oklahoma and Arizona, 1974
      - Philadelphia, 1974
      - Miscellaneous trips, daily schedules, 1975
      - Great Britain, 1974
      - England and Scotland, including some photographs, 1982
    - Correspondence, 1938-1939
      Letters from Alice to her family during her year long trip to Europe and the Middle East.
    - Miscellaneous personal materials
      - Pamphlets and brochures from Berkshire Summer School of Art, ca. 1920-1940
      - Certificate of acknowledgement
      - Travel summaries
      - Inscribed copy of Apostles Extraordinary: A Celebration of Saints and Sinners by Geddes MacGregor
      - Gift of Prayer book
  - Chronology of life and work of James T. Cleland (Box 32)
  - Books of prayers and sermons
  - Diaries, 1927-1928
  - Records of marriages in Duke Chapel, 1943-1966
  - Sermons, 1955-1956
  - Miscellaneous writings and correspondence
  - Bound volumes of sermons (Box 33)
  - Clippings
  - Poems based on the Bible
  - Subject files pertaining to Robert Burns
  - Cleland retirement, 1979
  - Tribute to Cleland, 1978
  - The Religious Ethics of St. Paul (Cleland's thesis) (Box 34)
  - Seminary notes, 1937-1938
  - Scotland, Amherst, and Duke sermons, 1926-1943
  - Epistle of Galatians (Greek vocabulary notes)
  - Thesis on the attitudes of the British church on the British coal dispute of 1926, 1928
  - Frame's lectures on St. Paul
  - Carillon chorale setting, inscribed, 1969
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1877-1906
    Contains mostly clippings.
Related Material
Divinity School records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel records. Administrative Committee records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel records. Renovation Committee records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel records. Sermons.
University Archives, Duke University.
Chapel records. Chaplain to the University records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Cleland committee (James T. Cleland Chapel Endowment Fund) records.
University Archives, Duke University.